Guide to the M. C. Stoner papers, 1827-1967 RL.11841
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
M. C. Stoner papers
1827-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11841
15 Linear Feet 12 boxes Approx. 17,071 items
Collection comprises correspondence, legal papers, business records, bills and receipts, photographs, writings, recipes, clippings, and other items relating to the life and career of businessman M.C. (Marshall Clayton) Stoner, of Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, and three generations of the Brewer and Stoner families from Pennsylvania and Maryland. Includes many speeches by George W. Brewer, a lawyer and senator in the Pennsylvania legislature, 1857-1859, and M.C. Stoner's father-in-law. Much of the correspondence and other items relate to coal mining and specifically to M.C. Stoner's Rocky Ridge Mining Company. There are also letters written to Stoner's daughter, Louise, chiefly from male friends.
Arrangement
Organized into the following groups: Correspondence; Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Company correspondence; legal papers; financial papers; writings; recipes; clippings; photographs; and volumes.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Maryland in 1853, M. C. (Marshall Clayton) Stoner was a businessman whose primary residence after the 1910s was in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania. He was involved in the grain and flour business, in real estate in Florida and Georgia, and in coal mining in Pennsylvania. In the 1890s he resided in Georgia, where he formed a company selling mining stock and securities. Although perhaps not reflected in these papers, he was reportedly one of the earliest owners of the Coca-Cola formula, and in Pennsylvania was an official of the Western Maryland Railroad.
Louise Stoner, M.C. Stoner's only child, became a published poet and linguist, and continued to live in the family home in Chambersburg until her death in 1971. She studied at Wilson College, the University of Florida, and the University of Havana in Cuba.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The M. C. (Marshall Clayton) Stoner papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1971.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises correspondence, legal papers, business records, bills and receipts, photographs, writings, recipes, clippings, and other items relating to the life and career of businessman M.C. (Marshall Clayton) Stoner, of Chambersburg, Pennsylvania. Includes many speeches by George W. Brewer, a lawyer and senator in the Pennsylvania legislature, 1857-1859, and M.C. Stoner's father-in-law. Much of the correspondence and other items relate to coal mining and specifically to M.C. Stoner's Rocky Ridge Mining Company.
Other materials, including early legal papers, pertain to three generations of the Brewer and Stoner families from Pennsylvania and Maryland. There are also letters written to Stoner's daughter, Louise, chiefly from male friends. Her writings may also be present in the collection.
Businessmen -- Pennsylvania -- Correspondence; Coal mines and mining -- Pennsylvania; Industries -- Pennsylvania -- Franklin County; Mines and mineral resources -- Pennsylvania; Chambersburg (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Franklin County (Pa.) -- Economic conditions; Franklin County (Pa.) -- History; Pennsylvania -- Commerce; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Photographs
- Correspondence, 1860-1911 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1912-1933 (Box 2)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1901-1903 (Box 3)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1904-1906 (Box 4)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 5)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1906-1907 (Box 6)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1906-1908 (Box 7)
- Rocky Ridge Coal and Mining Co: Correspondence, 1908-1909 (Box 8)
- Legal papers, 1827-1935 and undated (Box 8)
- Financial: General, 1856-1938 and undated (Box 9)
- Financial: Bounty accounts, 1864 (Box 9)
- Financial: George farm accounts, 1864-1884 (Box 9)
- Financial: Coal company accounts, 1901-1910 September (Box 9)
- Financial: Coal company accounts, 1910 October-1911, 1917-1928 and undated (Box 10)
- Writings, clippings, recipes (Box 11)
- Photographs, small volumes (Box 12)
- Oversize materials (Oversize-folder 1, Oversize-folder 2)
- Additional oversize materials (Tube 1)